<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the fifth monarchy. Proving by invincible arguments, that the saints shall have a kingdom here on earth, which is yet to come, after the fourth monarchy is destroy'd by the sword of the saints, the followers of the lamb. / Preached by Mr. Tho. Goodwin, on Rev. 5. 9, 10. By which it will appear, that it is for the same truth (that formerly was so much contended for) that some of the people of God suffer at this day. Published for the truths sake.</title>
            <author>Goodwin, Thomas, 1600-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E812_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207633</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866672</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866672</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E812[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the fifth monarchy. Proving by invincible arguments, that the saints shall have a kingdom here on earth, which is yet to come, after the fourth monarchy is destroy'd by the sword of the saints, the followers of the lamb. / Preached by Mr. Tho. Goodwin, on Rev. 5. 9, 10. By which it will appear, that it is for the same truth (that formerly was so much contended for) that some of the people of God suffer at this day. Published for the truths sake.</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, Thomas, 1600-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Livewel Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e., September] 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelations V, 9-10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118950:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
SERMON
OF THE
Fifth Monarchy.</p>
            <p>Proving by Invincible ARGUMENTS,
<hi>That the Saints ſhall have a Kingdom
here on Earth,</hi>
Which is yet to come, after the Fourth
Monarchy is deſtroy'd by the Sword of
the Saints, the followers of the LAMB.</p>
            <p>Preached by Mr. THO. GOODWIN,
on <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>By which it will appear, that it is for the
ſame Truth (that formerly was ſo much contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for) that ſome of the People of God ſuffer at
this day.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Truths ſake.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 24. 21.</bibl>
               <p>—And meddle not with them that are given to
change.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Livewel Chapman,</hi> at the Crown
in Popes-head-Alley. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118950:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118950:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He doctrine of the <hi>SAINTS REIGN ON
EARTH,</hi> is matter of <hi>great Comfort</hi> to the
People of God, becauſe of the glory which ſhall
be revealed in that day. This Sermon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to my hands, <hi>at ſuch a time as this,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the <hi>Truths of Chriſts Kingdom</hi> (this
Reign of the Saints) <hi>are SO blaſphemed and ſpoken againſt,</hi>
even by the <hi>quondam</hi>-Aſſertors and Profeſſors of them; and,
when men are become SCOFFERS; this term <hi>FIFTH-MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NARCHY-MEN</hi>
being made a mark of <hi>Ignominy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach:</hi>
I thought it my duty to communicate it to thee (Reader)
that <hi>the Truth may be vindicated,</hi> and <hi>the Saints comforted</hi>
in this evil day.</p>
            <p>This Excellent man hath proved this Truth by ſuch undeniable
Demonſtrations, that I am perſwaded all the Enemies Chriſt and
It hath, are not able to gainſay. To perſwade thee to ponder them,
I ſuppoſe I need not: the honour and eſteem the worthy Arthor
hath in the hearts of all good men that have either heard or read
him, will be a ſuffictent Motive.</p>
            <p>Onely give me leave to point out a few things to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are told, page</hi> 6. That the Saints have an influence in the
managing the affairs of the world, by their Prayers. <hi>If ſo,
let us conſider, what a</hi> TOTTERING CONDITION <hi>they
are in, who have the trayers of the Saints engaged againſt them;
yea, though but of a few</hi> deſpiſed ones, <hi>who are not clothed with
the glory and power of this world. I do remember that this good
man told us in another</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Preached <hi>Feb.</hi> 5. 1645. on <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. from ver. 1 to 5.</note> 
               <hi>Sermon,</hi> That the prayers of a few
Saints have a mighty prevalencie to turn the ſtate of affairs
in the world: The prayers of the Saints againſt thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:118950:3"/>
oppreſs them, will ſtill bring the vintage (<hi>the vintage of Gods
wrath on Proteſtants that provoke him</hi>) on them. An Angel
cries out of the Temple, ſeeing the Name of Chriſt profan'd
by thoſe that profeſs Chriſt, and yet are oppoſers of the
Saints: God hears their voice, and ſends it for them, and
will continue to do it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, we are told in the afore-mentioned page, <hi>That though
the Saints know not what Chriſt will do next, yet they are
guided (as it were) by a ſpirit of Prophecie, to ſeek for thoſe
very things which he is about to do.</hi> Then how cautious
ought we to be, of CENSURING thoſe of Gods people who go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
us in their prayers and deſires, lest we prove Oppoſers of the
Spirit of God in them!</p>
            <p>Again, page 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c. That the Saints in heaven rule the
world, and, by converſe with the Angels, have a knowledge
of the great things that are done on earth. When a ſoul is
converted, there is joy in heaven; and when</hi> Rome <hi>is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
there will be joy in heaven.</hi> Rev. 18. 20. <hi>and</hi> Rev. 6.
9, 10. <hi>The ſouls under the altar, newly ſlain, they cry to
God to avenge their blood.</hi> Now what may we think the
Saints in heaven (who within theſe ten yeers laſt paſt, loſt their
lives in the Cauſe of Christ) are EMPLOYED ABOUT at this
time, they underſtanding by the Angels what great—are
come to paſsion our earth! May we not juſtly fear,
they are crying to God, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt
thou not judge and avenge our blood!</hi> &amp;c. Surely things
are not now, as if <hi>THE GREAT INTEREST OF STATES
AND KINGDOMS</hi> were minded; the Impriſonment of
the Saints ſpeaks another kinde of language. But let us not be
diſcouraged: our Lord Jeſus hath foretold theſe things, that ſo
we might prepare our ſelves, and when they come to paſs, our hearts
may not be troubled. Theſe are ſignes of his coming; and many
more he gives us, that he is coming, and will not tarry. <hi>Come,</hi>
Lord Jeſus, come quickly. Even ſo. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By a ſervant of the Saints, who waits<lb/>
for, and expects the Kingdom and<lb/>
Power of our Lord Jeſus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118950:3"/>
            <head>A
SERMON
OF
The fifth Monarchy.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Revel. 5. 9, 10.</bibl>
               <q>And they ſung a new ſong, ſaying, Thou art worthy to take
the book, and to open the ſeals thereof: for thou waſt ſlain,
and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood, out of every
kindred, and tongue, and people, and nation:
And haſt made us, unto our God, kings and prieſts: and
we ſhall reign on the earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſcope of this whole Chapter is (as
I have ſhewed you heretofore) to ſet
forth (in the beginning of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie</hi>)
The ſolemnity of Chriſts under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
to be king, and to execute under God
all his decrees contained in this book, to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil
and accompliſh them, in governing this world to the end
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118950:4"/>
thereof, for the good of his Church.</p>
            <p>In the firſt verſe therefore, you have (all being act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in a Comick way) God the Father, ſitting upon a
Throne, holding a book in his hand: and (to glorifie
Chriſt the more, that he alone was able to undertake
the execution of the things contained in that book) a
Proclamation was made, Who in heaven or in earth
was able to open the book, and to looſe the ſeals
thereof: ſo verſ 2. In this ſtrait, (becauſe none was
found worthy to do it) Jeſus Chriſt ſteps up, and
takes the book out of the hand of him that ſate upon
the throne: ſo verſ. 7. And then, from verſ. 8. the
Chapter is ſpent in the acclamations of the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
of all ſorts, which are caſt into three ſeveral
Rings or Rounds, ſtanding round about the throne.
There is firſt the acclamation of the Church of men
on earth, verſ 8, 9, 10. There is ſecondly the accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
of the Angels, ſtanding round about the
Church of men, in a Ring remoter then they from
the throne, verſ. 11 &amp; 12. And then you have the
common multitude that do ſtand without, <hi>every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
in heaven, and in the earth, and in the ſea,</hi> all ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<hi>Praiſe and glory to him that ſuteth on the throne, and
to the Lamb, for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am yet in the acclamation of the Church of men
on earth, contained in the 8, 9, and 10 verſes. Where
you have, firſt, their deſcription, verſ. 8. Secondly,
the ſong which they ſing, in the 9 &amp; 10 verſes; and
that for two things: firſt, becauſe that the Lamb had
redeemed them: ſo verſ. 9. and ſecondly, for advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
them to be kings and prieſts unto God. And
then laſtly, you have an Inference, or a triumphant
concluſion they collect from all what they had ſeen;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118950:4"/>
and that is this: <hi>WE SHALL RAIGN ON
EARTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I finiſhed that of <hi>Redemption,</hi> a day or two ago.</p>
            <p>I came ſecondly to their Advancement: <hi>Thou haſt
made us, unto our God, kings and priests.</hi> There are theſe
things to be obſerved in it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the perſons that are made kings and prieſts,
<hi>US,</hi> the generality of Saints.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhewed you what it was to be a king
and a prieſt.</p>
            <p>Kings they were,</p>
            <p>1. In regard of the inward frame of their ſpirits.
And</p>
            <p>2. In reſpect of the outward Royalty which he
beſtoweth upon them, as upon Kings.</p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt himſelf is here preſented both as a
King, and as a Prieſt; as a Lion, and as a Lamb ſlain:
and anſwerably, he makes the Saints partakers of the
priviledges which he himſelf hath. <hi>Thou haſt made us</hi>
(ſay they) <hi>kings and prieſts.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt himſelf is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
a King; he hath it by inheritance: ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 4.
He <hi>hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name then
the Angels:</hi> but we are <hi>made,</hi> and made by him. He
is the Heir; but we come in through him to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs
with God: ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>See and acknowledge the prerogative of Jeſus
Chriſt above all the Saints. Though all the ſame
priviledges that are in Chriſt himſelf, are in the
Saints; we are ſons as he, we are kings as he, prieſts
as he: yet all theſe with this difference; he is <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
ſo,</hi> we are <hi>made ſo,</hi> made ſo <hi>by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 5, 6. when the Apoſtle would prove that
Chriſt is a Prieſt, and hold forth that title of his, he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118950:5"/>
quoteth two places; and a man would wonder why
thoſe two plaees ſhould be put together: Firſt, verſ. 5.
ſaith he, <hi>He that ſaid, Thou art my ſon, to day have I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
thee. As he ſaith</hi> (ſo verſ. 6.) <hi>in another place, Thou
art a prieſt for ever after the order of Melchizedek.</hi> How
doth the firſt of theſe places, <hi>viz. Thou art my ſon,
this day have I begotten thee,</hi> prove that Chriſt was a
Prieſt? Thus: The law of Nature, before <hi>Moſes,</hi>
was, that the eldeſt, the firſt-born in the family, was
both the Judge, and alſo the Prieſt of that family.
Now becauſe Chriſt is both the natural and the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
Son of God, therefore he is a Prieſt by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;
but we (I ſay) are made ſo by him.</p>
            <p>And take this for a certain Rule, That that which
is derived, can never arrive to that fulneſs of preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
with what is natural. An adopted ſon can never
come to be a natural ſon. A made King and a made
Prieſt, can never come to the ſame height of prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
and title that he hath that is naturally ſo. And
therefore though all that is in Chriſt, and all his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
are by way of participation in the Saints,
yet it is impoſſible they ſhould be in that fulneſs:
Why? Becauſe it is derived: <hi>Thou haſt made us kings
and priests.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thou hast made us, unto our God, kings and prieſts.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>I take it, thoſe words, <hi>unto our God,</hi> do not refer to
Kings, but to Prieſts, and to that alone: and my
reaſon is this; Not onely becauſe it cannot in any
propriety of ſpeech be ſaid, <hi>We are kings unto God:</hi>
We may be ſaid to be kings unto the creatures, and
unto all things elſe. But to be <hi>Prieſts unto God,</hi> to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
up ſacrifice unto him, that is proper. And the
reaſon further is this, Becauſe in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 6. (where
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118950:5"/>
this thing is fulfilled) though he ſpeaks there of their
raigning, and of their being Kings, yet he doth not
ſay they are Kings unto God, but onely ſaith, <hi>They are
prieſts of God, and of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Prieſts they are <hi>unto OUR God;</hi> becauſe that
God becomes their God by a free choice, though in
Chriſt, yet not for Chriſt: We are choſen in Chriſt,
but not for the merit of Chriſt; he is our God
freely.</p>
            <p>I told you that theſe words, <hi>Thou haſt made us
kings and prieſts,</hi> reſpect eſpecially their priviledge and
honour to rule this world, and the affairs thereof.
When they ſaw Jeſus Chriſt undertook the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
the affairs of the world, and to execute the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees
contained in that book held in the hand of him
that ſate on the throne, which contained how God
would have the world managed unto the day of
Judgement, and that Chriſt was thus crowned king;
they upon this utter this ſong of praiſe, That <hi>they
are made kings with him;</hi> as in reſpect of the glory to
come in heaven, being co-heirs with Chriſt, ſo alſo
as being joyned in commiſſion with him for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging
of the affairs of this book, and accompliſhing
the things contained in it. <hi>We alſo</hi> (ſay they) <hi>are
kings and priests.</hi> And their inference implies as
much, <hi>We ſhall raign on earth:</hi> the loweſt interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of which, that can be given, muſt be this: We
ſhall have an hand in guiding the affairs of the earth;
which although it ſhall have an eminent accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
at a certain ſeaſon to come, therefore they ſay,
<hi>We SHALL raign:</hi> yet notwithſtanding they are
kings at preſent, and it is in ſome degree fulfilled
now.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118950:6"/>
I told you laſt day, I thought there were four de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
of the fulfilling of this their being Kings.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in this world, they by their prayers having
an influence in the managing the affairs of the world,
and into the accompliſhment of all the great things
that Chriſt doth do for his Church. And though it
may be, and it is certain, they have not in all ages
known (according to what is in this prophecie) what
Jeſus Chriſt will do next, yet ſtill, by the ſpirit of
Prophecie, as it were, the Saints have been guided
to ſeek for thoſe things at the hands of God and
Chriſt, which he was about to accompliſh.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in heaven; and for that I quoted firſt
that place in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 26. where, <hi>To him that over cometh,</hi>
(therefore it is meant of a ſtate after death) <hi>and keepeth
my commandments to the end, will I give power over the
nations, and he ſhall rule them with a rod of iron: as a
veſſel of the potters ſhall they be broken in ſhivers, even as I
have received of my Father.</hi> When is this to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled?
Not before death; for he ſpeaks of him
that overcometh, and keepeth his commandments to
the end. Not at the day of Judgement onely; for it
is the ſame promiſe was made to Chriſt in the ſecond
Pſalm, which is evidently to be underſtood of
Chriſts Government committed unto him by the
Father until the day of Judgement, which here you
ſee he ſaith he hath received of his Father. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that in the ſecond Pſalm be meant (as clearly it
is) of Chriſts government of the world unto the day
of Judgement, and that he promiſeth his Saints after
death the ſame priviledge; then of neceſſity it muſt
needs follow, that they have a ſhare and a hand
therein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118950:6"/>
I quoted likewiſe another place for this, namely,
out of <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 17. where when that great buſineſs, the
greateſt work then in the world, was to be done, the
cutting down of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and turning him
out for ſeven yeers to feed among the beaſts of the
field, the Angel that comes down, and gives the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
for it, ſaith, <hi>This matter is not by me alone, but it
is by the decree of all the watchers, that is, of all the angels,
and by the word of the holy ones:</hi> they all concur in it.
And thus <hi>Junius</hi> interprets that place.</p>
            <p>I added likewiſe, for the ſtrengthening of this, a
third Scripture, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. 9, 10. where the ſouls under
the altar, newly ſlain, having their ſouls ſevered from
their bodies, under that great and laſt perſecution
under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> (for to thoſe times doth that cry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer)
they cry for vengeance upon their blood: Not
onely doth their blood cry, as <hi>Abel</hi>'s is ſaid to do
from the beginning of the world, but their ſouls
are ſaid to cry.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts, that they may bring in the doctrine
of the invocation of Saints departed, (which is that
great doctrine of devils, or of <hi>Daemons</hi> rather, which
the Apoſtle foretold ſhould be brought up in the
world, and is the greateſt idolatry that ever was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
earth) they teach that the ſouls in heaven do there
know all things here below, in the glaſs of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
and of the Godhead. And our Divines, that
they may wholly take away that Argument for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation
of Saints, from the Papiſts, many of them
have denied that there is any knowledge at all of the
things that are done here belowe. But, my brethren,
there is no connexion between their knowledge of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118950:7"/>
the great affairs of this world, and having an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
into them; and their invocation, none at all.
For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, no man is able to affirm that they know all
particular things here: and yet me-thinketh no man
ſhould deny, but that they have knowledge (by the
Angels that are continually meſſengers from heaven
to earth) of the great things that are done here.
There is joy thorowout all heaven, when a ſoul is
converted. And in <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 20. when <hi>Rome</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
as there will be joy thorowout the whole
earth, ſo there will be joy thorowout the heavens al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
when that City is ruined, in which is found the
blood of all the Apoſtles, and of all the Martyrs and
Saints ſlain by the power and authority of that City
(for ſo God hath ordered it) from the Primitive times
to this day; then ſaith he, <hi>Rejoyce over her, thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
and ye holy apoſtles and prophets: for God hath aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
you on her.</hi> I ſay, there is no connexion between
thoſe two; That becauſe they may be ſuppoſed to
know ſome of the great affairs of the world, that
therefore they muſt be invocated. Invocation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
is upon theſe grounds denied by our Divines,
and juſtly too: For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is certain, and cannot be denied, that the
Angels do know the things of this world; for they
attend there as miniſtring ſpirits continually, which
the other do not: and yet becauſe they know them,
it is no argument at all, that therefore we may invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
Angels, or pray unto them to pray for us. If a
man were ſure that an Angel were by him, and now
attending on him, (as I am certain there are Angels
attending the Saints; for they are their great guard
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118950:7"/>
in all places, eſpecially in the Churches, in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Worſhip) yet he hath no warrant at all to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
that Angel to pray for him: God hath not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
ſuch a way of communion between us and
him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we have no warrant to believe that the
Saints in heaven do hear us when we pray unto them
to pray for us; and leaſt of all, to think that one
Saint ſhould be able to hear a thouſand, nay ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
Saints on earth at one time; it is the greateſt
abſurdity in the world to imagine it: and yet how
many ſuitors hath that one virgine <hi>Mary?</hi> The
Saints departed may be ſuppoſed to have a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
and priviledge, and participation with Jeſus
Chriſt, and a great honour communicated to them,
for the managing of the great affairs of this world;
and yet there is no conſequence, nay the clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
that therefore we ſhould invocate them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
that no man can be aſſured, nay it is certain
they do not hear the prayers of any, much leſs can
they hear the prayers of ſo many: which is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But laſtly, it is flat Idolatry, and that for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
Becauſe that Chriſt being aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
is conſtituted and appointed a Mediator there;
and therefore for any to pray to the Saints in heaven
to pray for them, is to have another Mediator before
Chriſts face, whereas he alone hath took on him that
office: for, <hi>There is one mediator between God and man, the
man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo now I paſs from the Explication of thoſe
words; and come to the third thing, which, I take it,
is more eminently aimed at in the text, and in theſe
words,
<q>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118950:8"/>
                  <hi>We ſhall raign on earth.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall open what I conceive to be the meaning of
theſe words, exceeding briefly, not intending to make
a Subject of any thing in this Chapter. For when I
firſt took it in hand, I onely purpoſed to run curſorily
over it.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, it is evident, that there muſt be ſome
great eminent advancement, yet to come, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent
of Chriſts being King; which theſe Saints
here, had in their eye.</p>
            <p>This I ſhall open to you by degrees.</p>
            <p>For firſt, if you mark it, upon Chriſt's taking the
book, (which was his undertaking to be King of the
world) they fall out into this Outcry of praiſe and
rejoycing, <hi>We ſhall raign on earth.</hi> This is the fruit,
this is the iſſue, this is the concluſion of Chriſt's ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
taken the kingdom, and undertaking to be King.
And it muſt needs too be ſome great and eminent
thing, which muſt have an eminent and conſpicuous
accompliſhment: for it is that thing which is next in
their thoughts. They over-look all priviledges elſe,
and do pitch upon this, and parallel it with Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.
For, if you mark it, their ſong of praiſe runs
but upon theſe two things; <hi>Thou haſt redeemed us with
thy blood, and hast made us kings,</hi> and <hi>we ſhall raign on
earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is ſome eminent thing, to be fulfilled
at an eminent time to come. For mark the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;
<hi>Thou haſt made us kings,</hi> ſay they; thou haſt
given us that title, and that honour at the preſent: but
<hi>we SHALL raign;</hi> ſpeaking of it, as of a thing yet to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118950:8"/>
come. They are kings, and they do raign in that
reſpect by prayer; but yet they raign in ſackcloth:
yea, but <hi>we SHALL raign,</hi> ſay they.</p>
            <p>Now that you may the better underſtand how it
is to come, and when it is to come; for otherwiſe in
all other reſpects the Saints are Kings in all ages; but
I ſay, that there is a peculiar time in which it is to be
accompliſhed, which they have now in their eye.</p>
            <p>To make this clear to you, do but conſider the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
contexture of what now followeth in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>They utter this, you ſee, in the beginning of the
book, in this viſion of Chap. 5. which (as I have
ſhewn) is the prologue to the whole that follows.
They utter it when they did but firſt ſee Jeſus Chriſt
undertake to be King of the world, and had taken the
government thereof upon him, and the execution of
the decrees contained in that book he took out of the
hand of him that ſate on the throne. Before the end
of the world ſhould come, there was a long time,
and a great many things that were contained in this
book, in this roll which Chriſt took, which was
written within and without, that were orderly one
after another to be performed; therefore, in the
next Chapter to this, after this Viſion is paſt, (which
as I ſaid, is the prologue) there is firſt a going forth
to conquer; <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith he, verſ. 2.) <hi>a white horſe,
and he that ſate on him had a bowe, and a crown was given
unto him; and he went forth conquering, and to conquer.</hi>
He had begun to ſet upon the world then, he went
forth conquering; but he muſt go on to conquer;
for he had the Heatheniſh world to conquer, and he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118950:9"/>
hath the Antichriſtian world, and he hath the Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metane
world to conquer. And all his conqueſt is
carried on, till towards the later end, by his bowe;
he takes nothing out with him elſe; he overcomes
by his Word, which are <hi>the arrows he ſhoots into the
hearts of the Kings enemies,</hi> as you have it in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 5.
So that now all the ſtory thorowout this book after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
it is but the ſtory of Chriſts conquering of
his Kingdom with his bowe, and with his arrows,
and executing the decrees that were contained in the
roll he took out of his Fathers hand. When you
come towards the end of the book, in the 19 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
he that in the ſixth Chapter you ſaw when he
went firſt out, riding upon a white horſe, you ſhall
ſee him with Armies attending of him, whereof he
is the General, riding likewiſe upon a white horſe.
<hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſaith he, verſ. 11.) <hi>heaven opened, and behold a white
horſe, and he that ſate upon him was called Faithful and
True; and in righteouſneſs he doth judge and make war.</hi>
For towards the later end, when he comes to grapple
with the Antichriſtian world, he doth do it by the
Sword, and not by his Bowe onely. And therefore
when he ſpeaks of the Beaſt (chap. 13.) who had made
war with the Saints, he tells us, (verſ. 10.) that <hi>he that
killeth with the ſword, muſt be killed with the ſword.</hi> It
ſhall be the ſword that ſhall end it. Therefore he
that at firſt went forth upon a white horſe, with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but his bowe, you ſee him in the nineteenth
Chapter coming to make war, &amp; the Armies which
were in heaven following him. And what is the
iſſue of it? Verſ. 20. <hi>The Beaſt was taken, and with
him the falſe prophet,</hi> (whether the Mahumetane party,
and the Pope, I will not now determine; but) <hi>they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118950:9"/>
were altogether ruined and deſtroyed, caſt into a lake of fire
burning with brimſtone.</hi> All this Jeſus Chriſt doth,
before he comes fully to poſſeſs his kingdom. And
this you have related to you between the 6 Chapter
and the 20 Chapter.</p>
            <p>Well now, at the 20 Chapter, you ſhall ſee, that
what they ſaid at the beginning would be the iſſue of
Chriſt's taking upon him the government of the
world, and undertaking to fulfil the Decrees contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in the book, the ſame is declared to be made good
then, as being the eminent ſeaſon for it. For after
that he had taken the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, an
Angel came down from heaven, (ſo verſ. 1.) having
the key of the bottomleſs pit, and a great chain in his
hand; and he lays hold on the dragon, that old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
which is the devil and Satan, and bindes him a
thouſand yeers, and caſteth him into the bottomleſs
pit, and there ſhuts him up, ſets a ſeal upon him, that
he ſhould deceive the nations no more, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And
then, verſ. 4. <hi>I ſaw thrones, and they ſate upon them, and
judgement was given unto them. And I ſaw the ſouls of
them that were beheaded for the witneſs of Jeſus, and for
the Word of God, and which had not worſhipped the beast,
neither his image, neither had received his mark upon
their foreheads, or in their hands: and they lived and
raigned with Chriſt a thouſand yeers. But the rest of the
dead lived not again, until the thouſand yeers were finiſhed.
This is the firſt reſurrection. Bleſſed and holy is he</hi> (verſ. 6.)
<hi>that hath part in the firſt reſurrection; on ſuch the ſecond
death ſhall have no power; but they ſhall be prieſts of God
and of Chriſt, and ſhall raign with him a thouſand yeers.</hi>
Mark; what they ſay at the beginning, when they
ſaw Jeſus Chriſt undertake the Kingdom; the very
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118950:10"/>
ſame (after he had conquer'd all his enemies, the Beaſt
and the falſe Prophet, and then taken the devil and
all, and flung him for a time into the bottomleſs pit)
is here fulfilled. That which before they ſaid would
be the iſſue of Chriſts government, is here in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ſame terms ſaid to be accompliſhed. Here in the
5 Chapter they ſay, <hi>Thou hast made us kings and priests;</hi>
in Chap. 20. 6. they are ſaid to be <hi>priests of God, and of
Christ.</hi> Here they ſay, <hi>And we ſhall raign on earth:</hi> in
the 20 Chapter it is twice repeated; firſt, verſ. 4. <hi>They
raigned with Christ a thouſand yeers:</hi> and again, verſ. 6.
<hi>And they ſhall raign with him a thouſand yeers.</hi> This, I
ſay, ſhews it evidently that at the beginning they had
this in their eye, as that which ſhould be the iſſue
and cloſe of Chriſts governing the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But you will ſay,</hi> Is what is ſaid in Chap. 20. meant
of the Saints raigning on earth?</p>
            <p>Certainly yes: and the reaſon is this, Becauſe
during this raign, Satan is ſaid to be bound. Now
to have Satan bound while the Saints raign in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
is unneceſſary and needleſs: for how can he
diſturb them, or be an annoyance to their kingdom
there? Whereas you ſee, that by way of prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to this kingdom they ſhall have on earth, both
the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet are taken, and Satan
himſelf bound. Neither, ſecondly, can it be meant
of the raign of the Saints in heaven; for that is for
a longer time then a thouſand yeers; and thoſe Saints
that were ſlain in the Primitive times, they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
raigned longer then a thouſand yeers. But
that which doth moſt clearly evince it, is this, That
in the 7 verſe the devil is ſaid to be let looſe: <hi>And
when the thouſand yeers are expired,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Satan ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118950:10"/>
be looſed out of his priſon.</hi> Therefore it muſt neceſſarily
be meant neither of the kingdom of heaven after the
day of Judgement, nor of the kingdom of heaven
before the day of Judgement; but of a kingdom
which they ſhall have on the earth, as the words are
in this 5 Chapter.</p>
            <p>Me-thinks (my brethren) that thus much ſhould
be evident to all mens apprehenſions, by paralleling
the words uſed here at the beginning of Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
of the government of the world, and the
words expreſſed at the later end, (<hi>viz.</hi> in Chap. 20.)
when Chriſt had thus accompliſhed the decrees con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
in the book. I ſay, Me-thinks thus much
ſhould be conſpicuous to all mens underſtandings,
That there is ſome eminent kingdom for the Saints
after all; when the enemies of Chriſt, the Beaſt and
the falſe Prophet, and Satan himſelf is overthrown;
when the decrees of this book are accompliſhed,
when the time of this Prophecie is run out, that then,
I ſay, there is an eminent kingdom for the Saints to
have on the earth. Thus much, I ſay, me-thinks
ſhould be evident to any mans underſtanding: It is
that which in the beginning theſe ſay will be the end
of Chriſts kingdom here; it is that which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
themſelves withal; and, it is that which in order
followeth Chriſts accompliſhing the decrees of his
Father, and the ruine and deſtruction of his enemies.</p>
            <p>There have been thoſe that have made this to be
already fulfilled, namely, That there hath been a
time wherein the Saints in heaven that were killed in
the Primitive times, had a great deal of honour put
upon them for a thouſand yeers; and the Saints on
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118950:11"/>
earth had a great deal of peace; which they compute
to be from the time of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, till
the perſecution aroſe afreſh by the Pope and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian
party; and they reckon it to be about a
thouſand yeers.</p>
            <p>But it is evident, that that is not the meaning. For
the time of this Raign here ſpoken of, muſt be after
the Beaſt is deſtroyed: for in the 19 Chapter, verſ. 20.
it is ſaid, <hi>The Beaſt was taken, and caſt into the lake:</hi> and
then follows in the 20 Chapter, their <hi>raigning with
Christ a thouſand yeers.</hi> And likewiſe all the Vials men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
in the Chapters before, were firſt to be pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
out upon him: and therefore it cannot be during
the Popes raign. And then again, it cannot be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
that time neither, becauſe it is ſaid that the devil
is bound up, that he ſhould deceive the nations no
more: Now during the raign of the Beaſt, Satan
never deceived the nations more then then: ſo Chap.
13. 13. <hi>He deceiveth them that dwell on the earth.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
did he deceive men more both with Idolatry and
Superſtition, never was there raiſed more Wars and
Perſecutions againſt the Saints, then during the raign
and time of Popery. The Saints indeed have had a
great deal of honour put upon them by the Papiſts,
in Canonizing of them, and the like; but alas, it
was all but a falſe honour, it is not the honour and
priviledge that the raigning with Chriſt a thouſand
yeers gives them; neither would they have ſo rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
in it when Chriſt firſt took upon him to be king;
not rejoyce, I ſay, in that glory and honour which
the Popiſh world gave them during thoſe times of
Popery; no, <hi>We ſhall raign on earth,</hi> ſay they: this
was it which was the ground of their rejoycing, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118950:11"/>
which they had then in their eye. Therefore as
this was not begun when theſe Saints here in the
5 Chap. firſt ſpake it; ſo neither ſhall it begin
until the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet be deſtroyed.
You muſt firſt ſee the accompliſhment of thoſe
great things that are written in this Book concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Antichriſt and his Kingdom, which will be
the cloſe of the Kingdom of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
Jeſus Chriſt, and then follows that which
you have in the 20 Chap. the 4, 5. and 6. verſ.</p>
            <p>The next Queſtion will be, What perſons he
ſpeaks this of, when he ſaith, We ſhall reign on the
Earth?</p>
            <p>Clearly, of thoſe that are redeemed unto God
by the blood of the Lamb, Chriſt Jeſus, out of
every Kindred, and Tongue, and People, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But the great Querie will be, whether they ſpeak
this of themſelves, perſonally, or whether they
ſpeak it of all the Saints, ſucceſſively? that is,
not onely we now, but all the Saints in many ages
to come, ſhall be perſecuted and oppreſt: as we
were by Heatheniſh <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo they ſhall be under
Antichriſtian <hi>Rome;</hi> (for in <hi>Rome</hi> is found the
blood of all the Saints; therefore I do not ſo much
fear any Proteſtant-perſecution) yet in the end,
though we now by our blood lay the foundation,
and do but ſow to it; yet there is a crop to come
up one day of a Kingdom which Jeſus Chriſt hath
undertaken to bring into this world, which his
Saints ſhall have.</p>
            <p>You may very well interpret it ſo; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
for my part I take it to be that which was their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118950:12"/>
aim. And the language of the Scripture doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
as much. <hi>We ſhall not all die,</hi> (ſaith Paul) <hi>but
we ſhall be changed.</hi> Did <hi>Paul</hi> think to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
the day of Judgement? No, yet he ſpeaks
in the perſon of <hi>We,</hi> and the Chriſtians then might
have ſaid the like; and yet thoſe perſons all died.
He meaneth therefore, the whole Community and
Fellowſhip of the Saints, whom the Apoſtle
<hi>Peter,</hi> in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. calleth a Generation, and a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
and therefore now, as a Nation that knows
that one day they ſhall prevail and have a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
as the <hi>Jews</hi> think, (though they ſuppoſe it
many yeers to come, and do not think that they
themſelves ſhall enjoy it) yet ſpeaking in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of their Nation and Generation, may ſay,
We ſhall one day be the top of Nations, and have
theſe and theſe Priviledges: that is, Not we that
now live; but all of this Nation, this Generation,
this Kindred, as they are called alſo. And thus it
hath a paſſable and a fair interpretation; <hi>We ſhall
reign on earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the plain Doctrine or Obſervation is
but this, <hi>That there is in the end a Kingdom to come
here for the Saints,</hi> that after all the Kingdoms of
the World have had their time and their date, by
which the Saints have all along been oppreſt and
injured, there is, even on earth, a Kingdom to be
given unto them, when all Nations ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
unto God, and the Saints in them be the
prevailing party in the World. The Scripture
ſeems to run much this way.</p>
            <p>The firſt man (that I finde of an Engliſhman)
that diſtinctly fell into this Notion, was a man of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118950:12"/>
much holineſs and piety,<note place="margin">Mr. Wood.</note> now with
God. I'll tell you the occaſion that
led him into theſe thoughts, as he himſelf (in a
manuſcript I have lying by me) expreſſeth it. <q>I
went, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> to recollect all the promiſes that
are in the whole Book of God made unto the
Saints, beginning at <hi>Geneſis</hi> and ſo going along
throughout all the old Teſtament (not dreaming
of any ſuch notion as this is) &amp; I found no check
at all in my thoughts, until I came to read ſome
of the Prophecies in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> which profeſſedly
ſpeak of the times of the Goſpel, &amp; which ſpeak
ſuch great, high, and glorious things of ſpiritual
enjoyments of God, with outward peace &amp; proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity.</q>
As now to give you an inſtance or two,
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. from verſ. 3, and ſo on: <hi>In the laſt dayes the
mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top
of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the hills,
and all nations ſhall flow unto it: and they ſhall beat their
ſwords into plough-ſhares,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neither ſhall they learn
war any more.</hi> The like you have in <hi>Micah</hi> 4. the
whole Chapter. So in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 6, 7, 8. when the
vail ſhall be taken from off the hearts of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
(as <hi>Paul</hi> interprets it in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.) he tells you of
the peace and glory that ſhall be in that nation, and
how the Lord will wipe away tears from off all
faces, and the rebuke of his people ſhall be taken
away from off all the earth; whereas before they
ſhould lie under all ſorts of reproaches over all the
World. Likewiſe in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 9, 10, and ſo to the end,
you have promiſes of all ſorts to this purpoſe,
how that the gates of the Church ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
open, <hi>they ſhould not be ſhut day nor night, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118950:13"/>
men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>may bring unto thee the forces of the
Gentiles, and that their kings may be brought: for the
nation and kingdom that will not ſerve thee, ſhall periſh;
yea, thoſe nations ſhall be utterly wasted. The ſons alſo
of them that afflicted thee, ſhall come bending unto thee,
and all they that deſpiſed thee, ſhall bow themſelves down
at the ſoles of thy feet, and they ſhall call thee, The city
of the Lord, The Sion of the holy One of Iſrael. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
thou has been forſaken and hated, ſo that no man went
thorow thee, I will make thee an eternal excellency, a joy
of many generations. Thou ſhalt alſo ſuck the milk of
the Gentiles, and ſhalt ſuck the breſt of kings. For braſs I
will bring gold and fortron I will bring ſilver, and for
wood braſs, and for ſtones iron. Violence ſhall no more
be heard in thy land, wasting nor destruction within thy
borders; but thou ſhalt call thy walls, Salvation, and
thy gates, Praiſe. The Sun ſhall be no more thy light by
day,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo in <hi>Iſa. 65. 16, 17. He who bleſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
in the earth, ſhall bleſs himſelf in the God of the
earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for behold, I create new heavens and a new
earth, and the former ſhall not be remembred, nor come
into minde. Behold, I create Jeruſalem a rejoycing and
her people a joy: and the voice of weeping ſhall be no more
heard in her, nor the voice of crying. There ſhall
be no more an infant of daies, nor an old man that hath
not filled his daies. And they ſhall build houſes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit
them; and they ſhall plant vineyards, and eat the
fruit of them,</hi> &amp;c. So in <hi>Zech. 14. 9. The Lord ſhall
be King over all the earth: in that day there ſhall be one
Lord, and his Name one.</hi> I cannot ſtand to ſingle out
thoſe things in theſe Chapters and many others of
the like kinde, which are moſt emphetical; you
may do it when you read them. <q>Now, <hi>ſaith he,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118950:13"/>
when I read theſe promiſes (as likewiſe that in
<hi>Dan.</hi> 7. that after all the four Monarchies,
(whereof the remainder of the fourth ſtandeth)
ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>the kingdom, &amp; dominion, and the
greatneſs of the kingdom under the whole heaven ſhall
be given to the people of the Saints of the moſt High.</hi>)
When I found ſuch promiſes, (<hi>ſaith he,</hi>) as theſe
are, I knew not what to think, I wondred at it,
and was amazed.</q> Hereupon, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> he read ſome
Commentators, whom he found to expound them
all of Heaven and the glory thereof, ſet out in an
allegorical way: but yet this ſatisfied him not;
for it ſeemed evident to him, that it was to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
of a Kingdom here on the Earth; for he
perceived there was mention made of ſinners, and
of men that die, and the like: and therefore read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
other interpretations, he found them apply it
to Ordinances, and and other Spiritual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of God, with abundance of outward peace
and proſperity. Hence therefore he concluded
that there muſt neceſſarily be a time in which theſe
promiſes muſt be fulfilled and accompliſhed; <hi>for
the Saints have alwaies in all ages been more oppreſt
under the Goſpel, then ever they were under the Law;</hi>
they have propheſied in ſackcloath, and have been
the outcaſt, and the reproach of all the Kingdoms,
and are ſo accounted even to this very day. <hi>Daniel</hi>
you know was a Court-like Prophet; for he lived
in the alteration of thoſe great Monarchies, the
Aſſyrian to the Babylonian, and the Babylonian
to the Perſian; and God did reveal himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
to him; for you ſhall finde his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
ſpent moſt in deſcribing the four Monarchies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118950:14"/>
that ſhould be in the world; the deſcription you
ſhall finde ſpecially ſet down in the 7 Chapter,
where having deſcribed the three firſt Monarchies,
he cometh at the 23 verſ. to the fourth, the fourth
Beaſt, which he ſaith ſhall be the fourth King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
upon Earth, which ſhall be divers from all
Kingdoms, and ſhall devour the whole Earth, and
ſhall tread it down and break it in pieces, as the
Roman Empire did, the Reliques whereof remain
in the Turk &amp; Pope to this day. But after all theſe
Beaſts were ended, <hi>I beheld</hi> (ſaith he, verſ. 11.) <hi>even
till the Beaſt was ſlain, and his body deſtroyed, and given
unto the burning flame.</hi> For in <hi>Rev,</hi> 19. the Beaſt is
taken, and ſo there is an end of him. And as for
the other Beaſts, he ſaith, <hi>They had their dominion
taken away, yet their lives were prolonged for a ſeaſon.</hi>
But in the end and concluſion of all, what ſaith
he? <hi>I ſaw one like the Son of man,</hi> (verſ. 13.) <hi>and there
was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom,
that all people, nations, and languages ſhould ſerve him;
his dominion is an everlaſting dominion, which ſhall not
paſs away, and his kingdom that which ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
And verſ. 27. <hi>The kingdom, and dominion,
and the greatneſs of the kingdom under the whole heaven,
ſhall be given to the people of the Saints of the moſt High.</hi>
The text you ſee is expreſs, that the Kingdom here
ſpoken of, is a Kingdom which the Saints ſhall
have after the four Monarchies are deſtroyed,
which he ſaith ſhall be a kingdom, <hi>not in heaven,</hi>
but, <hi>under the whole heaven,</hi> where there are People,
Nations and Languages, men, who ſhall continue
in their ſeveral varieties, which in Heaven they do
not; for there is neither Tongue, nor Kindred, nor
Nation there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118950:14"/>
Let me ſpeak another thing to you. Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
once with a Papiſt, who defended (as you
know they do) the truth of their Religion, and
the ſupremacy of the Roman Church, he brought
this Argument to me. <q>Read (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
you ſhall finde ſome of them make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of a Mountain that ſhall be ſet upon the top
of all the Mountains, to which all the people of
God ſhall reſort in a conſpicuous manner; that
peace and outward proſperity ſhall attend and
accompany that Church or Mountain, the riches
of the Nations ſhall be brought into it, Kings
ſhall bow down their heads unto it, and lick the
duſt of their feet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) were
theſe and the like prophecies ever fulfilled, if not
in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And for my own part, I muſt acknowledge, that
let any one read ſuch prophecies as theſe are, and
give me an anſwer how or when they either are or
can be fulfilled, unleſs this be granted for a truth,
<hi>That after all is done, there is kingdom to be given unto
the Saints upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you come to deal with the <hi>Jews,</hi> you ſhall
finde, that they alwaies knew and expected, and
do now know and expect, a kingdom to come for
them in the end. The Apoſtles themſelves ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to have ſuch thoughts; for in <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 6, 7.
when Chriſt was about to aſcend into Heaven,
they ask'd him, <hi>Lord, wilt thou at this time restore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
the kingdom to Iſrael?</hi> Chriſt you ſee doth not
deny that there was a kingdom to come for them,
onely he ſaith, <hi>It is not for you to know the times and
the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his own power.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118950:15"/>
Plainly intimating, that there was a time and a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
which God had for it, which he reſerveth in
his own power. And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> when he
comes to deal with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and preach the Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah
to them, in <hi>Act.</hi> 3. knowing that their great
miſtake lay in looking that the Meſſiah ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
from the firſt come to them as a glorious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,
and reſtore to them the kingdom, and not
come meek and lowly, as he did, riding upon an
Aſs, he deals with them according to their own
Principles, onely removeth their miſtake:
<hi>Repent ye</hi> (ſaith he, verſ. 19.) <hi>and be converted, that
your ſins may be blotted out, when the times of referſhing
ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, and he ſhall ſend
Ieſus Chriſt, which before was preached unto you, whom
the heaven muſt receive, until the times of the reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of all things</hi> (The very word which the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
uſed in <hi>Acts 1. Wilt thou not reſtore,</hi> ſay
they?) <hi>which God hath ſpoke by the mouth of all his
holy Prophets ſince the world began.</hi> You <hi>Iews,</hi> ſaith he,
expect a reſtitution; but here is your miſtake; this
Jeſus muſt firſt be preached, and he muſt go into
Heaven, and the Heaven muſt receive him, till that
time of reſtitution cometh, and then he will at
leaſt manifeſt himſelf unto you. He that wrote
that little book called, <hi>The Voyage into the Levant,</hi>
he ſaith, That he had often occaſion to converſe
with the <hi>Iews,</hi> whom he generally found to be in
expectation of their Meſſiah; and when he told
them of theſe kinde of notions that were up and
down this Kingdom and other places of <hi>Europe,</hi>
concerning a Kingdom that God would give unto
his Saints here upon the Earth, after the calling of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118950:15"/>
the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that their Meſſiah would manifeſt
himſelf unto them even according to their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations;
he ſaith, They were infinitely taken
with the hearing of it. It ſuiteth with all their
Notions, and with their Expectations, and with
all the Interpretations the Rabbins have given of
thoſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And conſider one thing more: All ſorts, almoſt
out of all quarters of the world, though they
run ſeveral waies, yet they fall all into this Notion.
As now for inſtance: Thoſe that are for the Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of Churches to their firſt purity, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
for this reigning for a thouſand yeers, and
that the Saints ſhall have thrones given them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
There is a time coming, ſay they, after Antichriſt
is down, when there will be a reſurrection of
Churches to their firſt purity and glory, in which
there ſhall be onely Saints, without mixture of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
And ſo they interpret that place in <hi>Rev.</hi>
20 5, 6. <hi>This is the firſt reſurrection: bleſſed and holy
is he that hath his part in the firſt reſurrection.</hi> And,
ſay they, Until then, all Churches will be but as
dead things: the great reſurrection is reſerved till
that time. Others that are for the coming of
Chriſt in Spirit, (as the language of ſome is) they
ſay this alſo, That towards the end of the World,
Jeſus Chriſt will break forth to his people with a
great deal of glory and ſplendor, ſo as never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
The very Jeſuites themſelves have been ſo
much convinced, that ſuch things are to be in
the later daies, that ſome of them have written a
book of the fifth Monarchy; onely indeed they do
apply and appropriate it unto themſelves, and call
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118950:16"/>
that kingdom which, they ſay, ſhall be in thoſe
daies, <hi>Regnum Jeſuiticum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſcope I have in ſaying this, is to ſhew you,
that although men run ſeveral waies in their expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
and expectation of this time, the <hi>Jews</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
one way, the Papiſts another, and thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
our ſelves ſeveral waies; yet as it is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
and a ſtrong one, That there is a God,
and that the Notion of a Deity is ſtamped in the
Spirits of men, becauſe all Nations have pitched
upon worſhipping of ſome God, although their
error hath been to worſhip the falſe: ſo the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety
of waies that men have run, and the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
that men are in, of ſuch a time coming as I
ſpeak of, it argueth ſtill for the ſubſtance, that
there is ſome ſuch thing, although one miſtake,
and another miſtakes, and perhaps none can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly
tell what is to come. This I am certain
of, that the Primitive Chriſtians did abundantly
comfort themſelves with this Notion, and the
conſideration of it. And here you ſee the Saints
had it in their eye at the very firſt, when Chriſt
took the Government of the World upon him, as
that which ſhould be the cloſe of his Kingdom:
<hi>We,</hi> ſay they <hi>ſhall reign on the earth;</hi> there is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
reſerved for our Generation; ſpeaking (as
I ſaid) in the language of the Communion of
Saints.</p>
            <p>And there is all the reaſon in the World for it,
beſides what I have mentioned out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Saints that have been oppreſt here in
this World, it is a righteous thing with God to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118950:16"/>
give that Generation reſt, and that they ſhould
have their turn after all Kingdomes are diſſolved;
that what <hi>Adam</hi> loſt, ſhould be reſtored to them
again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, That all thoſe promiſes which (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren)
have had an accompliſhment but in an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
way, as that which Chriſt, &amp; which the</hi> Pſalms
<hi>alſo mention,</hi> The meek ſhall inherit the earth: <hi>That
all the prayers that have been put up, as,</hi> That thy
will be done on earth as it is in heaven: <hi>That</hi> Abraham
and his ſeed ſhould be heirs of the world: <hi>That</hi> there
ſhall be a new heaven, and a new earth, in which righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
dwelleth; <hi>which, ſaith</hi> Peter, we look for: <hi>and
that promiſe, if you look in</hi> Iſa. 65. <hi>I am ſure you
will finde to be</hi> made to men on earth; <hi>for he ſaith
plainly,</hi> They ſhall build houſes, and inhabit them; and
they ſhall plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are thoſe that go yet further, and ſay, That
though there is ſuch a Kingdom belonging to the
Saints, yet they ſay withal, That the Saints that
have been before, they ſhall during that Kingdom
riſe again; ſo interpreting that place in <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.
according to the very letter: <hi>I ſaw the ſouls of them
that were beheaded for the witneſs of Ieſus, and for the
word of God, and which had not worſhipped the Beaſt,
neither his image, neither had received his mark upon
their foreheads, or in their hands; and they lived and
reigned with Chriſt a thouſand yeers: but the rest of
the dead lived not again till the thouſand yeers were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.
This is the first reſurrection.</hi> Which reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
that ſhall thus uſher in this reign, ſome
interpret of a generation of Saints a multitude of
Converts that ſhall come with the ſame Sprit and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118950:17"/>
Power that all the Saints formerly beheaded,
had; and ſo they are ſaid to riſe again in them, as
<hi>Elias</hi> is ſaid to riſe again from the dead in <hi>Iohn
Baptist,</hi> who came in the Spirit and Power of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias.</hi>
But there are theſe reaſons given to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
and that it muſt be meant of a true Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
and of a Reſurrection taken in a proper
ſenſe: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is ſaid, That <hi>the ſouls of them that were
beheaded, they lived;</hi> how? by a reſurrection; for
he ſaith, It <hi>is the first reſurrection.</hi> Now, how do
ſouls riſe? no way, but by having their bodies
united to them. They are the ſouls of men that
have been killed, and killed by the ſword: now
their Reſurrection muſt be anſwerable to their
death; it is made the reward of it. Their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
lives were taken away, their Reſurrection to
life therefore, muſt be taken in the ſame ſenſe and
proportion to the life which they loſt. And then
again, obſerve, it is the very ſame ſouls, in which
you ſhall finde a great deal of emphaſis: for read
the 6 Chap. verſ. 9. <hi>&amp;c. I ſaw,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the ſouls
of them that were ſlain for the word of God, and for the
testimony which they held, lying under the altar, crying
with a loud voice,</hi> &amp;c. They were the Primitive
Martyrs; for this was in the beginning of the
book. Now here in the 20 Chapter he ſaith, <hi>I
ſaw thoſe ſouls,</hi> or <hi>the ſouls of them that had been ſlain,
for the witneſs of Jeſus, and for the word of God:</hi> he
uſeth the ſame deſcription; and he addes to them
(for the 6 Chap. is meant of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
ſlain under heatheniſh <hi>Rome</hi>) thoſe that had
been ſlain under Antichriſtian <hi>Rome;</hi> for he ſpeaks
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118950:17"/>
of ſuch as had purified themſelves from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,
and which had <hi>not worſhipped the Beast, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
his image, neither had received his mark upon their
foreheads, or in their hands, and they</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>lived
and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand yeers. But the rest
of the dead lived not again.</hi> No wicked men ſhall
riſe then; they are reſerved until the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But to what end is this?</p>
            <p>Firſt, That as theſe Saints do now govern the
World inviſibly (as I ſaid before;) ſo they may
then do it viſibly. And great muſt needs be the
glory and happineſs of thoſe times.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which the Angels do now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibly,
the Saints ſhall then do viſibly. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
now have this World ſubjected to them, and
all the affairs thereof; and the execution of the
Decrees of God, are ſtill ſaid to be done by them.
But, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb. 2. 5. Unto the Angles,
God hath not put in ſubjection the world to come, whereof
we ſpeak.</hi> And he doth not ſpeak of the World to
come after the day of judgement; for it is that
Kingdom which Chriſt ſhall have before he giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
up all things unto the Father. This world
here, therefore, is ſubjected unto the Angels that
do miniſterially rule, and who do work with the
Spirits of men this way and that way for the good
of the Church, in oppoſition to Satan. But then all
ſhall be done by the Saints in a viſible maner.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Hereby they are made conformable to
the ſame ſtate and condition Jeſus Chriſt was in:
whilſt he was in the World, he was mean, he was
under all ſorts of oppreſſion; he dies, his Soul goes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118950:18"/>
to heaven; he riſeth again, and after he was riſen, he
ſtays here below for many days, converſeth with
his Diſciples at times, inſtructeth them in the
things of the Kingdom of God, appeareth, diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if you ask me, What will the life
of men be, thus riſen? I ask, What was the life that
Jeſus Chriſt led during thoſe forty dayes before
he did aſcend? And if you object, that this will
be a diminution to their happineſs; I anſwer,
It was no diminiſhing of the happineſs of Jeſus
Chriſt. Aſſuredly, he injoyed more bleſſedneſs
being riſen, and his Soul and Body united, then
when his Soul ſingly and alone was bleſſed; and
yet, for thoſe forty dayes he was here upon the
Earth. Think my brethren, of the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
whenas Jeſus Chriſt himſelf will come with
all his Saints and Angels, out of the place of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
into this viſible World; and it will ask a long
time to judge the World, becauſe he will judge
it as a man, and lay open the ſecrets of all hearts;
and we may be ſure that will be done in this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
World. The Angels that come down from
heaven to earth, do yet ſee the face of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it is no derogation to the happineſs and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs
of the Saints.</p>
            <p>And if you ask me. Whether during this time
they ſhall eat and drink? I anſwer, The children
of the Reſurrection neither marry nor give in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
or do any ſuch thing; but they are as the
Angels of God. Chriſt after his Reſurrection
lived not upon any ſuch thing; no more ſhall the
Saints, although the number of them upon the
earth ſhall be innumerable; for the earth ſhall be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118950:18"/>
full of the knowledge of the Lord, and the
Name of God and of Chriſt ſhall be ſet up in the
whole earth; and the greater part of the World
ſhall be Saints. And though thoſe that ſhall then
be found alive, may haply eat, and drink, and
build houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet thoſe that riſe again, ſhall
not.</p>
            <p>I have, as briefly as I could, opened this thing to
you, which here theſe Primitive Chriſtians, in the
very beginning of the book, have in their eye.
Whether it be meant onely of that generation of
Saints, and of the Reſurrection in the 20 Chap. or
onely a Reſurrection by way of ſucceſſion, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon
of former times; or whether, yea or no, it
ſhall be a true and proper Reſurrection, I leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determined:
onely this I ſay, That certainly there
is ſome great thing (after all the Kingdoms of the
world have had their turnes) for the Saints to have,
and that on earth, both by the promiſes in this
book, and by all the prophecies of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
which have been ſince the World began.
And therefore, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Seeing we expect ſuch
things, what manner of perſons ought we to be, in all holy
converſation and godlineſs!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
